בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is צדי ג', Tzadi Gimmel,
and we pick up at the bottom of צדי ב' עמוד ב',
Tzadi Beis Amud Beis, we have an interesting discussion over שבת Shabbos
around how this idea of a large yard and a small yard
has ramifications beyond just הלכות שבת. Hilchos Shabbos. The idea that the—and
the way I understood it there was actually like I said two
constructs going on. One is that the smaller yard, again with a
configuration like this... so it's not just about being smaller, it's about
the fact that this one is totally—we'll call this A and we'll
call this B—that B is totally open to A, but A is
not totally open to B. So that has two implications. One is
that there's no way that B can divorce itself what's going on
from A, but A can divorce itself from what's going on in
B. A good example of that is the last discussion about where
excrement and saying the שמע. Shema. If you're saying שמע Shema in
A and there's excrement in B, well B doesn't have to relate
to you because it's not
totally—you're only partially open. And the reverse—you're saying שמע Shema in B
and there's excrement in A, you can't disassociate those in B from
what's going on from A. That remnant, that's also directly relevant to
the whole point of the משנה, Mishna, that if you're not allowed
to carry in A and you find yourself in B, you can't
carry in B either because you are
totally not divorced from A. It's פרוץ במילואו. parutz bimlo'o. The other
aspect that the גמרא Gemara seems to be—the גמרא Gemara seems to
put these all together but in my mind they were sort of
distinct points that were being made is that B is an adjunct
to A, but A is not an adjunct to B. And therefore,
for example, if there's a מניין minyan in A then B is
the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur is in B, or there's a majority
of the מניין minyan in A and a minority in B, then
that can—because it's an adjunct—it connects with what's going on in A,
but the reverse cannot be true. If the מניין minyan is here
and the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur is here, well the מניין minyan
is the main thing, so therefore you cannot have the שליח ציבור
shliach tzibbur be sort of associated with B
because
the sort of secondary thing has to be in the adjunct space
and not the reverse. So similarly if you have a majority of
מניין minyan here and a minority here, that won't work because you
can't pull A after B. B can be pulled after A, A
cannot be pulled after B. So those were I think the two
models. The גמרא Gemara seems to sort of unify them, but at
least in my mind it's helpful to think about them as two
points: one is primary and adjunct, and the other as sort of
whether you can disassociate or not. What do you want to say,
Joe?
I would say it's just one.
Well that's the whole point is that from the perspective of B
it is one. If you're standing in A—look, if you view yourself
you're here, you're a person standing in A, and this is more
helpful, here's what you see.
Okay? And then you see like a yard over here. Okay? But
that's what you see if you're standing in A, so you don't
necessarily see that as related to you, right? But if you're standing
in B,
from the B side, well all that you see is
this. Right? Here's your walls here.
And then all that you see, as Joe says, is you actually
see it as... how do you see it? You actually see it
as one.
You don't see those walls. Yeah, you don't see those walls.
If you're standing here.
No, the ones that are off to the right of the entrance.
You don't see them.
You just see one wide open space.
You see a wide open space, right, not walls. You see the
far wall.
Right, right, exactly. You don't even see it. So that's exactly the
point, Kel. If you're standing in B, it all looks like one
space. And that's exactly why you can't disassociate yourself. But if you're
standing in A, then "Oh well that's not B, that's some other
space. I have to walk through the door to get there." Okay?
And that's exactly the point.
Doesn't it also depend on where in A you are? If you're
in the corner...
All right, we have to make one determination. Now let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says.
So, אמר ליה אביי. Amar lei Abaye. So אביי Abaye who was
sitting amongst these three rabbis who were all his seniors said to
them, אם כן מצינו מחיצה לאיסור, im kein matzinu mechitza le-issur, a
מחיצה mechitza makes it more forbidden. Now where have we seen that?
So anyway it's a discussion of רש"י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafos, but basically
the consensus is that the way the מחיצה mechitza makes it more
forbidden is that one scenario we said is
if you have a vineyard here—okay, I don't know how we're going
to demonstrate a vineyard, we'll make a little cluster of grapes—okay, you
have your vineyard here.
Kind of like a wall between them, people carrying.
Right, exactly. You have your vineyard there, okay? So that makes it,
we said, as if the vineyard here is a vineyard, that there's
a כרם kerem here, especially from the perspective of B, right? So
it's as if the כרם kerem extends here. And because the כרם
kerem extends here, if you want to plant wheat, okay or whatever,
then that's כלאיים, kilayim, right? That's what we said. All right, so
because—and especially elaborating on תוספות's Tosafos point that the prohibition is לא
תזרע כרמך כלאיים. Lo tizra karemcha kilayim. So כרם kerem extends in
here and you can't plant wheat over here. Now אביי Abaye understands
that
as we're about to see the normal הלכה halacha is, let's say
you had no walls. Okay? Let's say you basically just had your
rows of grapes here, you had your grapes and you had no
walls. Can you plant wheat? The normal הלכה, halacha, I know that
doesn't exactly look like wheat but you get the idea, the normal
הלכה halacha of where you can plant wheat is... You can plant
wheat as long as you are four אמות amot away from the,
from the, from the row of vines. Okay, now what אביי
Abaye understood is that what that that the statement in the what?
That if you enclose it, the whole thing becomes a כרם. kerem.
Right. Exactly. If you however enclose it, okay, like this, exactly, if
you enclose it, then it all becomes a כרם, kerem, because of
this, and this is an adjunct of that, then if this is
a כרם, kerem, this is a כרם, kerem, and even if it's
four אמות amot away, it's no good. אביי Abaye understood that they
said you can't plant wheat anywhere in the smaller one, because it
all becomes part of the כרם. kerem. And therefore, אביי Abaye says,
the מחיצה mechitza is making it more forbidden. But if anything, you
know, the fact that the מחיצה mechitza goes down here and down
here should cut it off more. But what actually you're telling me
is that by configuring it as an adjunct, it makes it even
more forbidden. Is that possible that a מחיצה mechitza creates pro- you
know, makes something more associated rather than more separate from one another?
So that's אביי's Abaye challenge. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says.
אמר ליה, Amar leh, okay. Where are we? Okay, one minute, one
minute. אמר רב זירא לאביי. Amar Rav Zeira le-Abaye. So רב זירא
Rav Zeira said to אביי, Abaye, did I skip you? ולא מצינו
מחיצה לאיסור? Velo matzin mechitza l'issor? שמעלה אין מחיצה מרחיק ארבע אמות
וזורע. Shema'aleh ein mechitza marchik arba amot vezorea. That without the מחיצה
mechitza you'd just be four אמות amos away. אילו הכא אסורה. Ilu
hacha asura. Now it's forbidden even outside of four אמות. amot. אמר
ליה רב זירא, Amar leh Rav Zeira, so רב זירא Rav Zeira
said to him, אביי, Abaye, who was one of the three rabbis
there, ולא מצינו מחיצה לאיסור? Velo matzin mechitza l'issor? Are you tell
me to me that you never find this elsewhere that a מחיצה
mechitza actually rather than making it more separate makes it more combined?
התנן, Hatnan, we taught. חצר גדולה שנפרצה לקטנה. Chatzer gedola shenifretza le-ketana.
גדולה מותרת קטנה אסורה. Gedola mutereset ketana asurah. מפני שהיא כפתחה של
גדולה. Mifnei she-hi k'pitacha shel gedola.
Okay.
So, we got our case where we started with, our whole משנה,
Mishna, which is exactly this, our whole משנה Mishna is only that
case up for four אמות. amot. We have our whole case the
exact same thing about the big one and the small one.
And it says, what does it say? It says that this one,
A, is okay to carry, right in A, even if they don't
have an עירוב eruv with B, because they're distinct from B, right?
That's what we said. Okay, so so far מחיצה's mechitza not an
איסור, issur, מחיצה mechitza allows A to be separate. But then he
goes on and says, ואילו השוה את קיפופיה גדולה נמי אסורה. v'ilu
hishveh et kipifeha gedola nami asura.
But if you, if you sort of leveled off the overhang, A
would also be אסור. assur. Let's say you made a new- you
extended a wall like this. Okay, and now here's your A. Now
A is forbidden. Right? Right? If you did that, you got it,
you made a new wall here in A's courtyard. So then for
this space over here, that's forbidden because that's now completely open to
B. So the מחיצה mechitza made A forbidden. You added a מחיצה
mechitza and A became more forbidden. So that's like an- there's an
easy answer to that. Let's see what the answer is. אמר ליה,
Amar leh, he said back to him, התם סילוק מחיצות הוא. hasam
siluk mechitzot hu.
So there you added a wall, but the effect of adding a
wall was removing walls. Yeah. By adding this wall, you removed these.
So you actually- the addition of a wall didn't make it more
separate, it made it more combined because it removed the presence of
some other walls. It removed these walls, right, which are helpful in
defining it as separate. But in this case all you did was
you brought things together.
Okay, so you did not- your adding of the מחיצה mechitza here,
you added this wall, and you added this wall, and you've created
a problem. Okay, whereas here by adding a wall you've removed other
walls, and therefore that's not a proof against me. Okay, my point
though is that when you actually do something that should make it
more separate, you've managed to make it more combined. Here by adding
these walls you removed others and you've made it more combined. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רבא. Amar leh
Rava. So רבא Rava said to אביי. Abaye. Now some want to
say the גירסא girsa should be רבה Rabba because he was one
of the rabbis of the group. ולא מצינו מחיצה לאיסור? Velo matzin
mechitza l'issor? Are you telling me you've never had a מחיצה mechitza
that makes it forbidden, meaning that brings stuff more together rather than
more apart?
דהא איתמר, Deha itmar, it was taught, דף עט עמוד א. daf
ayin tes amud aleph. סיכך
על גבי אכסדרה. Sikekh al gabei achsadra. You put סכך s'chakh
on top of a portico, that good old portico that we've been
discussing here and there. שיש לה פצימים. She-yesh lah patzimim. And it
has certain types of like
what do you call it? It has like these
I don't know what you call פצימים, patzimim, but anyway, cross- not
a beam, but anyway, a
corner. כשרה, Keshera, it's
kosher. ואילו השוה את פצימיה פסולה, V'ilu hishveh et patzimeha psula, it's
פסול. pasul. What does that mean? It means the case is
a very funny picture in רש"י, Rashi, ignore it, it's confusing. Okay,
they have a ריטב"א Ritva here. You've got a case of you've
got a portico. So it's got and it's got two walls is
the way רש"י Rashi explains it. And on the other two walls
it's got these, you know, posts, okay? And you went ahead and
you made סכך. s'chakh. Now, it's not a כשר kosher סוכה sukkah
because it only has two walls. But the good thing is, ignore
these posts here, that at this corner, okay, you've got a wall
that goes a little bit in the other direction, okay, and here
too, you've got a wall that goes a little bit in the
other direction. So actually, to make it more easy to understand, to
make it two-dimensional, it looks like this.
Okay,
these are the פסימין. psamim. Okay, I don't know how they translate
the word, but anyway, these little... these little shoulders essentially. Shoulders, whatever.
Okay. So and we know that a... what? Rashi calls them posts.
Doorposts. Anyway, anyway, we know that a סוכה, sukkah, you can have
two and the third one can be even a little bit. So
that's כשר. kosher. That's the way רש״י Rashi explains. תוספות Tosafot has
a different פירוש. peirush. But he says, look, I'll show you that
you can add a wall and make this סוכה sukkah פסול. posul.
How do you add a wall and make a סוכה sukkah פסול?
posul? Add a wall like this.
Okay? So now, your... now you only have two walls to your
סוכה, sukkah, right? You don't have two and a half. So the
answer is the same. That's not... that's not fair. That adding of
a wall removed this wall. So in other... not the adding of
a wall removing another wall. It's like the other case. That's not
a fair example. In this case, you actually added a wall and
you've only added a wall and it created a פסול. psul. Here,
by adding the wall, the problem was created because it effectively removed
the other wall. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
לימא תיהוי תיובתא דאביי? Lima tehavei tiyuvta d'Abaye? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
so אביי Abaye says, לדידי כשרה. Lididi keshera. First of all, in
general, in the case of the portico, I think it's כשרה. keshera.
That's a debate over in סוכה Sukkah which says which אביי Abaye
says and we have this before that the edge of the roof
of the portico, the פי תקרה pi tikra is יורד וסותם, yored
v'sotem, goes down. Yeah, well that's why some keep the גרסא girsa
of רבא Rava because רבא Rava and אביי Abaye we know debated
this issue. So he says, by the way, for me, first of
all, it's not a question to begin with. I think even if
you do that, it's כשר kosher because I think the beam on
the top is considered to go down and make a wall, פי
תקרה יורד וסותם. pi tikra yored v'sotem. לדידך, Lididach, according to you,
that you think it is פסול, posul, it doesn't matter. The reason
it's פסול posul is סילוק מחיצות. siluk mechitzot. You're removing the walls
of the פסימין. psamim.
You were talking to Mar, but this is רבא.
Rava. I understand, I understand. That's what bothers תוספות. Tosafot. Anyway, so
he basically says, look, so far the two examples you've given me
is that what by adding a wall, you've made it worse because
the adding of the wall removed other walls. You know, but I
am asking you how you explain this case where the adding of
the wall makes things more of a problem where it did not
remove other walls but actually should have separated the space off but
really what has it done is that it unified the space to
me, says אביי, Abaye, that is very bizarre. Okay. Yes.
By the nature of separating off one space is... is excluding some
within and separating without, so it's restrictive.
Right. So what you're saying is... is that the... it's not you
don't understand his answer here, but you don't understand why this is
so conceptually problematic. Okay. It's very nice. You say, well, these walls
should separate that out a little bit more. Yeah, fine, but these
walls pull it all together. Right. I get it. I understand. So,
you know, but looking at it, I guess two-dimensionally and, you know,
the fact that in some ways we say that separate. But I
agree with you that, you know, but that is what's bothering אביי.
Abaye. But I agree, forgetting the... rejecting the comparisons makes sense, but
the question itself is not so troubling. Let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with it.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רבה בר בר
חנה בר רב חנה לאביי. Amar leh Rabba bar bar Chana bar
Rav Chana le-Abaye. So רבה בר בר חנה Rabba bar bar Chana
said to אביי, Abaye, ולא מצינו מחיצה לאיסורא? Velo matzinu mechitzah le-issura?
Are you telling me we don't have a מחיצה mechitzah that comes
and creates a problem? והתניא, Veha tanya,
we taught
in a ברייתא, braisa, בית שחציו מקורה וחציו אינו מקורה. Bayit she-chetzyo
mekureh ve-chetzyo eino mekureh. Again, a כלאים kilayim case. You have a
house that half of it has a roof, the other does not
have a roof. גפנים כאן מותר לזרוע כאן. Gefanim kan mutar lizro-a
kan.
So if you have vines under the roofed part of the house,
you can plant seeds under the unroofed part of the house because
the existence of the roof effectively divides the two halves of the
house. A type of a פי תקרה יורד וסותם. pi tikra yored
v'sotem. Okay, and enough certainly as a demarcator between, you know, the
vines on one half and the other stuff on the other half.
Right, and presumably... ואילו השוה את קירויו. Ve-ilu hishveh et keruyah. And
now this isn't adding a wall, this is adding a roof. But
he says, but look, if you... if you make a roof on
the entire house, over the entire house, so אסור, assur, it's forbidden.
So again, it's a, you know, there's an obvious answer to that
comparison. אמר ליה התם סילוק מחיצות הוא. Amar leh hatam siluk mechitzot
hu. By adding a roof, you've removed the wall created by half
of the roof, right?
So that's bracketed, obviously.
Yeah, that's pretty obvious, right? You've got your case here, right? You
have your whole house, right? This house had a roof on it,
okay, so... so that essentially made a type of a מחיצה mechitzah
down the middle and let you plant in half. By building and
adding on to the roof, you've removed the מחיצה mechitzah that half
of the roof created. So obviously that's going to be a problem.
But what I'm talking is not when you've effectively in all these
various ways removed a מחיצה, mechitzah, I'm talking about when you add
a מחיצה. mechitzah. Okay, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says like this. Is that it? No, we're not done. שלח ליה
shlelei רבא Rava לאביי l'Abaye ביד beyad רב Rav שמעיה Shmaya בר
bar זעירא. Zeira.
So רבא Rava who wasn't there—that's why again the earlier גרסא girsa
of רבה Rabbah could make more sense, but he presumably heard about
this debate, so he was more אביי'ס Abaye's colleague, so he sent
an answer to אביי Abaye through the hands of שמעיה Shmaya בר
bar זעירא. Zeira. I don't know. Yeah, whatever. It's an ongoing discussion.
ולא מצינו מחיצה לאיסור? V'lo matzinu mechitza l'issur?
Are you telling me we don't have מחיצה mechitza that creates an
איסור? issur? והתניא, V'hatanya, יש במחיצות הכרם להקל ולהחמיר. yesh b'mechitzos hakerem
lehakeil ulehachmir. Now this is almost exactly the same case or very
similar. There are ways in which the walls around a vineyard להקל
ולהחמיר lehakeil ulehachmir can be a leniency and can be a stringency.
כיצד? Keitzad? How is this? כרם הנטוע עד עיקר מחיצה, Kerem hanatu'a
ad ikkar mechitza, if you have a vineyard that's planted right up
to a wall, זורע מעיקר מחיצה ואילך, zorei'a mei'ikkar mechitza v'eilaich, you
can plant beginning at exactly the other side of the wall. So
they can be separated by only like an inch, only by the
wall itself. שאילו אין שם מחיצה, She'ilu ein sham mechitza, and this
is when a—how it proves מחיצה'ס mechitza's leniency, because had there been
no wall there, מרחיק ארבע אמות וזורע, marchik arba amos v'zorei'a, you'd
have to distance four אמות amos as we've said. וזהו מחיצות הכרם
להקל, V'zehu mechitzos hakerem lehakeil, this is a way a wall in
a vineyard can be lenient. It could allow you to plant right
up right up against the opposite side of the wall. That's if
you're on the opposite side of the wall, the presence of the
wall is a leniency. That makes sense. Guess where the wall's gonna
be a stringency? Not when you're on the opposite side of the
wall, but when you're on the same side of the wall. Okay.
ולהחמיר כיצד? Ulehachmir keitzad? How is it more מחמיר? machmir? How is
it more stringent? היה משוך מן הכותל יא אמה, Hayah mashuch min
hakoseil yod-alef amah, לא יהא זורע לשם. lo yehei zorei'a l'sham. That
if you're eleven אמות amos away from the wall, you can't plant
something else there. שאילמלא אין מחיצה, She'ilmalei ein mechitza, that had there
not been a מחיצה, mechitza, מרחיק ארבע אמות וזורע, marchik arba amos
v'zorei'a, four אמות amos would've been enough. וזהו מחיצות הכרם להחמיר, V'zehu
mechitzos hakerem lehachmir, and this is a wall which is stringent. So
now we're getting to the real problem of the whole question which
is: Here's the הלכה. halacha. You have your vineyard, okay, we'll call
these I don't know our—what are they called?—rows of vines. If you
have a wall here, right, then you can plant your wheat over
here right up against the wall and you're fine. Because you're on
the other side of the wall. So that makes the wall lenient.
But, if you're not on the other side of the wall, okay,
if you've got your vines here, what's—if you have no wall, where
can you plant your wheat? How far away? Four אמות, amos, right?
Here's your wheat stalk. But now you have put a wall. And
now you are planting your wheat on that side of the wall.
So as we said, well the presence of a wall might pull
them more together. And now what you need in order to plant
wheat is not four אמות, amos, you need twelve אמות. amos. Why?
We'll discuss exactly where that number comes from in a minute. But
the point is is that here the presence of the wall when
you're on the same side of a wall pulls it together and
the מחיצה mechitza actually creates a problem because without a wall four
אמות amos would have been enough. With a wall and on the
same side of a wall you need twelve אמות. amos. So he
said what's bothering you? We have that all the time that a
wall if you're on the same side of the wall the wall
actually creates more of a problem.
I don't know, did he answer or something?
I don't know. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said back to him,
לטעמך אוספא ממתניתין. l'taimeich osfa m'matnisin. According to you, why did you
ask me from a ברייתא? braita? You should've asked me from a
משנה! mishna! Okay. So he's saying better. Okay, so what's the משנה?
mishna? דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה, mishna, קרחת הכרם. karachas
hakerem. If you have a bald spot in the vineyard, meaning you
have vines—you have an unplanted space—but you have vines on either side,
not a vines and a wall, but vines on both sides of
this bald spot. בית שמאי אומרים כד אמות. Beis Shammai omrim chof-dalet
amos. If you want to plant in the middle of that bald
spot it has to be twenty-four אמות amos wide. ובית הלל אומרים
טז אמה. u'Veis Hillel omrim tes-zayin amah. It's enough to be sixteen
אמה. amah. מחול הכרם. mechol hakerem. How about the מחול? mechol? Right.
By the way, you know מחול mechol means like a circle, בתופים
ובמחולות. bitupim u'vimcholos. Right. But actually there's one of the interpretations in
the—by—in ספר דברים Sefer Devarim where it says מי האיש אשר נטע
כרם ולא חיללו. mi ha'ish asher nata kerem v'lo chillelo. So חז"ל
Chazal say חיללו chillelo means that did not go into the fourth
year of כרם רבעי kerem revai and you did not redeem it,
like to be—you know, when you
do—when you—because the word is like חולין, chulin, לחלל lechaleil means to
transfer the קדושה. kedusha. But some commentators say what it means is
you haven't yet had a chance to have the first harvest where
they would do these circle dances.
So מחול הכרם mechol hakerem is like the space around the vine
and there's this whole association of doing these circle dances around the
time of the harvest. Anyway, so what is this מחול הכרם? mechol
hakerem?
It says a מחול הכרם mechol hakerem is... so you've got your
walls
of your vineyard and you've got your—you don't go right up—you don't
plant your vines right up to the edge of the walls. You
need some space around it so that you can you know... Plow
and whatever. So this space here is the מחול הכרם. Machol Hakerem.
There's no wall there, it's just a space between the vine and
the wall, right? This is your מחול. Machol. Okay, so that's your
מחול Machol is the space around the vine. Whereas a קרחת הכרם
Karachas Hakerem is like a bald spot in the middle of somebody's
head is right there. Okay, so if you want to plant in
the bald spot in the middle, it needs to be 24, we'll
say בית הלל, Beis Hillel, 16 אמות, amot, because it's surrounded by
vines on all sides, so it's much more considered in the middle
of the vineyard. So you need a greater space to be considered
like it's its own space. Whereas the מחול Machol between the vines
and the walls there's only vines on one side, according to בית
הלל Beis Hillel you only need 12 אמות. amot. But again it's
the idea that because of the wall that pulls them together, it's
more than the four אמות. amot. In the middle it's 16 and
by the walls it's 12. Whereas if there were no walls at
all and was just open space, four אמות amot would have sufficed.
Okay, so
where were we? קרחת הכרם בית שמאי אומרים עשרים וארבע אמות ובית
הלל אומרים שש עשרה אמות. Karachas Hakerem Beis Shammai omrim esrim ve-arba
amot ve-Beis Hillel omrim sheish esrei amot. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai
says 24 and
בית הלל Beis Hillel says 16. מחול הכרם, Machol Hakerem, the walk
around the the space that you know you walk around the vineyard,
בית שמאי אומרים שש עשרה אמות ובית הלל אומרים שתים עשרה אמות.
Beis Shammai omrim sheish esrei amot ve-Beis Hillel omrim shtaim esrei amot.
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says 16 and בית הלל Beis Hillel says
12 אמות. amot. ואיזו היא קרחת הכרם? Ve-eizu hi Karachas Hakerem? What's
the bald spot? כרם שחרב אמצעיתו. Kerem shecharav emtzaito. The middle of
it is desolate, is not planted. אם אין שם שש עשרה אמה
לא יביא זרע לשם. Im ein sham sheish esrei amah lo yavi
zera lesham.
If there is not 16 אמה amah there, you cannot plant something.
היו שם שש עשרה אמה, Hayu sham sheish esrei amah, once there
are 16 אמה amah so it's considered its own space, then, you
can't plant right up against the vines, then, נותנין לו כדי עבודתו
וזורע. nosin lo kedei avodaso vezorea.
You have to give the workspace, meaning the immediate space next to
the vines which is the space you need to stand to sort
of tend to them and bring in like a plow, that you
have to remove yourself away and you can plant וזורע את המותר
vezorea es hamotar and you plant the remainder. Now what is the
workspace? ארבע אמות. Arba amot. Okay, so if you have an enormous
just vineyard, right, so you space so it's four אמות. amot. That's
considered to be, right, that's considered כדי עבודתו. kedei avodaso. And since
you're separating yourself this normal space, the minimum space you have near
the vine to tend to the vine, then any space after that
is outside of the vine's space. So that's your normal idea. Here
where you're in the middle because you're surrounded by vines on all
sides you need 16 in order that it be considered to be,
you know at least a minimum of 16 in each direction I
mean in order that it's considered to be not part of the
vineyard. Once you have that you can't plant right here, you can't
plant right up against the vines. Then you're allowed to remove yourself
from your four אמות. amot. So you basically go in four אמות
amot in each
direction and allowed you a space in the middle of what? Eight.
Right, eight by eight, right? So you've got an eight by eight.
Okay, so anyway that's where you're allowed to plant. You need the
16 by 16 to create it as I'm not plant you know
it's not like I'm in the middle of the vineyard it's my
own space but even when you have your own space you have
to be four אמות amot away from the vines. Okay, that's the
case of planting in the קרחת הכרם. Karachas Hakerem. Now
ואיזו
היא מחול הכרם? ve-eizu hi Machol Hakerem? What's the case about the
sort of the band around the vineyard? בין כרם לגדר, Bein kerem
legader, between the vineyard and the wall. שאם
אין שם שתים עשרה אמות לא יביא זרע לשם, She-im ein sham
shtaim esrei amot lo yavi zera lesham, if there's no 12 אמות
amot do not plant something else there. Because then again it's like
you're right in the vineyard. היו שם שתים עשרה אמות, Hayu sham
shtaim esrei amot, once there's 12 אמות amot that establishes it as
its own space,
נותנין לו כדי עבודתו, nosin lo kedei avodaso, you give it the
four אמות amot berth וזורע את המותר vezorea es hamotar and you
plant the rest. Now again by the way you understand why it's
the same idea meaning here after you've given yourself the four אמות
amot the berth, right, you're left with a space of eight אמות,
amot, right? Is that clear? In the same idea here you after
you move the four you have an open space of eight.
What is that?
Four and eight. I'm sorry. Here
you removed yourself four אמות amot from the vine then you had
a space that was still eight. So here too if the entire
thing is 12, if this is a wall let's say, the entire
thing is 12, so once you've removed yourself four, the minimum four,
you still have a space here of eight. What does that 12,
what does that? That's the minimum space between the vines and the
wall that בית הלל Beis Hillel requires to allow you to plant
in this open space. If it's less than 12 אמות amot between
the vines and the wall then you can't plant even if you're
11 אמות amot away because then you're just considered to be still
much too part of the vineyard. Once there's an open space of
12 אמות amot then it's considered to be independent of the vineyard
but then still you can't plant right up against the vine. So
בית שמאי Beis Shammai says I don't know just add eight אמות.
amot. Okay anyway four אמות amot whatever it is. All right so
anyway that's the basic conceptual idea. So now the גמרא Gemara says
so anyway look the wall makes it a problem. אלא התם לאו
היינו טעמא. Ela hasam lav hainu taama. That's not the reason. Still
you can't plant right up against the vine. תושבי שמשיס? Tushvei Shamshis?
I don't know. Just add a אגמות. agamot. Okay, anyway, it's formal,
whatever it is. All right, anyway, that is, so that's the basic
conceptual idea. So now the גמרא Gemara says, so anyway, look, the
wall makes it a problem. אלא התם לאו היינו טעמא. Ela hasam
lav hainu taama. That's not the reason there. The reason there is
נפישו, nefasu, it would seem like okay, that's a perfect answer, you
see that walls, especially by כלאיים kilayim in vineyards, make it all
one. But he says, it's not because the wall was pulling it
together. It's what is the reason? אלא, Ela, some have the word
אלא. ela. דכל ארבע אמות לגבי כרם עבודת הכרם, Dechol arba amos
legabei kerem avodas hakerem, four אמות amot near the vineyard is the
working of the vineyard, so that's too close for comfort. לגבי גדר
Legabei geder and next to the wall, the first four אמות, amot,
כיון דלא מיזדרען, kivan delo mizdaran, since you can't plant right up
against the wall because it'll sort of like you know it'll undermine
the you know the roots will get in and they'll undermine the
you know the foundation of the wall and also because you can't
get your plow near enough, אפקורי מפקירי להו, afkurei mafkir lehu, so
you sort of you renounce ownership over it like you're not going
to be using those first four אמות amot anyway and therefore they
have no significance, they're like off-limits regardless. דביני ביני Debeini beini and
therefore the space in between, אי איכא ארבע חשיבן ואי לא לא
חשיבן, ee ika arba chashivan ve-lo lo chashivan, if it's four it's
fine, if it's not enough. So what אביי Abaye basically says is,
we would say this is a great answer to אביי Abaye because
this shows you the wall pulls it all together. But אביי Abaye
says, no, presumably, I mean it's a little unclear exactly how he's
answering, but this is what he sounds to be saying. He's saying,
it's not because the wall pulls it together. Even if you had
not four walls, right, although you could still say even one wall
pulls things together, but let's simplify it and look at one wall
and you had here the vineyard. He says, it's not that the
wall pulls it together. It's that you need anyway to be four
אמות amot away.
And because of the wall, you can't plant you know in the
first four אמות amot regardless, in general it's assumed to be off-limits.
So therefore, once you remove the four אמות amot that's considered right
on top and the four אמות amot that's considered right on top,
you need to have a space here that is significant. If the
space is less than four אמות, amot, then it's trivial. So for
that space to be considered somehow significant and independent, that has to
be four אמות, amot, that leads to—I thought that was terrible—Why can't
he plant in the four אמות amot closest to the wall?
For the two reasons, either because the roots undermine the foundation of
the wall for practical reasons, not halakhic reasons, okay, or because you
can't plow. So therefore he says that's why you need twelve אמות,
amot, whereas if there was no wall, because you could plant anywhere
sort of you know anywhere after the first four אמות, amot, nothing
sort of says, oh I have to be going in this way
and pushes you sort of into that space. So presumably what he's
saying is, but that's not relevant here, because here you're planting way
over here, it's not an issue of are you too close to
the wall or not close enough to the wall. Here, practically, the
presence of the wall forces you into the vineyard space, okay, whereas
here you could be twenty אמות amos removed, okay, and nevertheless it's
conceptually the wall pulls it all together. And he doesn't like that
idea that this wall here, of course you know that some a
wall that should separate really has the effect of pulling it together.
Then I agree with Dov, I don't really see what the big
issue is, because it's not just this wall, right, if it were
just this wall you'd understand his question, right? It's presumably though the
presence of the other wall, right, if it was just this wall
then you'd understand how does a wall pull that stuff in? But
if it's this wall as well then you sort of then you
understand. But who knows? Maybe he understood that even without the back
wall, just that wall enough and it really is a pretty big
shocker. Okay, let's take a look now, that is the end of
that discussion. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
You see why they said נפישו?
nefashu? Well you don't know, but I mean they felt that there
was an answer, that it's not a big problem by the vineyard
we do see that the wall pulls it together. He did not
think that that was true, at least or should not be true
in this case. Okay. אמר רב יהודה: Amar Rav Yehuda: ג' כפיפות
זה בצד זה. Gimmel kefifos zeh betzad zeh. Okay, ושנים החיצונים מגופפין
והאמצעי אינו מגופף. ushnayim hachitzonim megufafin veha'emtza'i eino megufaf. Okay, so now
we are going to again use this idea of the overhang to
look not only at the הלכה halakhah of עירוב, Eruv, well this
is somewhat related to עירובין, Eruvin, but to other הלכות halakhos where
the idea of sort of primary and subservient or adjunct space. So
now we can forget about the vineyard, okay, and now we're going
to look at the following thing.
Basically he says, okay,
it says you've got this, you've got a space like this. Okay,
you've got your A, your B, and your C. So the two
outer ones
are
overhangs and the middle one has no overhang. Okay, and now what's
the relevance of the הלכה? halakhah? So he says like this, he
says,
so these are these יד החצר, yad hachatzer, but whatever, these lots.
Okay, I know, והאמצעי אינו
מגופף. veha'emtza'i eino megufaf.
יחיד בזה ויחיד בזה, Yachid bizeh veyachid bizeh, נעשה כשיירא ונותנין להם
כל צרכן. na'asah kesheyarah venosnim lahem kol tzorchan. Okay, so you have
an individual in each one.
Some take out the word כדאי. kradai. Now you might remember, of
course you all do remember, I'm teasing, that, okay, that there's one
person here, one person here, one person here, that if you have
a case about making a wall just with vertical or horizontal there
are... In a, you're out camping, you have very little supplies and
therefore they allowed you to, you know, you'd make a wall that's
just a series of posts, right, all the way all all around
or it's a series of strings, right, remember like all around. And
you say לבוד lovud and you do that all around. So it
said fine, you can do that up till בית סאתים, Beis Sasayim,
our famous בית סאתים. Beis Sasayim. But more than בית סאתים Beis
Sasayim we're not going to let you do that that's too big
of a space for these walls that are not serious walls, just
sort of pseudo, you know, fake walls as it were. That's too
big of a space unless you're a שיירא. shayara. Unless you are
a caravan. If you're a caravan, a group of people, then we'll
be much more lenient on you we'll let you make for the
three of you as big of a space as you want even
with these pseudo walls. So what's a caravan? Three people. So here
it is, you all came and you camped out in this valley
and you made yourself these pseudo walls, okay, like this. There's one
person in this space, you all claim these spaces as your each
one as your own. A says this is my space, B says
this is my space, C says this is my space. Fine. Are
you a caravan of and the whole combination here is more than,
I can't do that 50 figure. Anyway, that's more than בית סאתים,
Beis Sasayim, okay. That's greater than בית סאתים. Beis Sasayim. So is
that going to be okay or not? Or maybe each section is
greater than בית סאתים. Beis Sasayim. Is that okay? Do you have
three people here or do you have individuals here? So says who
is this, רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi?
Who is it saying this?
I don't know.
Anyway, רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
So says רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he says look, basically we say
that at least from the perspective of B, okay, B, you know,
everything that happens in the bigger space effectively is happening in B.
So it's like A is in B and it's like C is
in B because there's nothing at least from B's perspective that keeps
those people out. And therefore it's like there are three people in
B. And once there are three people in B, at least for
B it is considered a שיירא shayara and it can be as
large as you want. Okay, that's what he says.
Now
right, yeah, you know, that's a good question. I would have said
that once you have three people all in one space then everything
else becomes an extension of it and the whole combination can be
as big as they want. Rashi makes it sound like B's space
can be as big as it wants, but A's and C's space
not necessarily. Because everybody is in B. So B's space can be
as big as you want. Okay, אמצעי מגופף ושנים החיצונים אינם מגופפים.
emtza'i megufaf u'shnayim hachitzonim einam megufafim.
What if it's the opposite? The middle one is the bigger one
and the two ones are the smaller ones, don't have overhang, ויחיד
בזה ויחיד בזה ויחיד בזה, v'yachid b'zeh v'yachid b'zeh v'yachid b'zeh, אין
נותנים להם אלא בית שש. ein nosnim lahem ela Beis Shesh. You
only give them a total of of six, you know, six, which
is three בית סאתים. Beis Sasayim. So if you have it as
the reverse, I have a picture of it. Right, my thing doesn't
have it. Oh, really? Whatever. Okay, you got a plus sign essentially.
Okay, so you have your A, B, and C, and you've got
your one, one, and one. So basically these guys are not in
here. Therefore this from the perspective of A, maybe B is in
A, from the perspective of C, maybe B is in C, but
each one of these have two guys, B only has one guy
in his space, effectively. So nobody has three guys, so each person
just gets a בית סאתים Beis Sasayim and a בית סאתים Beis
Sasayim which is two סאה se'ah times three is, you know, two
times three is, the whole thing has six. Okay, that's that scenario.
Now, איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. Now they raise a question. Of course
that was too juicy to pass up. So אחד בזה ואחד בזה
ושנים באמצעי. echad b'zeh v'echad b'zeh u'shnayim b'emtza'i.
This same, this last scenario, if there were two in the middle,
מהו? mahu? What's the story? אי להכא נפקי תלתא הוו ואי להכא
נפקי תלתא הוו. ei l'hacha nafki tlata havay v'ei l'hacha nafki tlata
havay. If they go this way there's three and that way there's
three. או דילמא חד להכא נפיק וחד להכא נפיק. o dilma chad
l'hacha nafik v'chad l'hacha nafik. Or maybe we should imagine it as
that one goes into each direction. Okay, which is if you've got
here two in the middle and you're saying that from A's perspective
the people of B are in A and from C's perspective the
people of B are in C. So maybe ah A sees it
as those two guys are with him, there's three guys in A.
C sees it as those two guys are with him, there's three
guys in C. Or do you say no, A is looking at
B but maybe only one guy is coming to A, and again
wasn't coming but conceptually associated with A, one guy and the other
guy is associated with C, so each side only has two guys
and not three guys, so there's no שיירא. shayara. Okay, so what's
the story? So we don't know. So it says, ואם תמצי לומר
חד להכא נפיק וחד להכא נפיק. v'im timtzi lomar chad l'hacha nafik
v'chad l'hacha nafik. If you say in that case effectively each one
from B, one goes to each side and there's not three in
any cases. שנים בזה ושנים בזה ואחד באמצעי. shnayim b'zeh u'shnayim b'zeh
v'echad b'emtza'i. Two in A, two in C and one in B.
So מהו, mahu, what do you say there? השתא ודאי אי להכא
נפיק תלתא הוו ואי להכא נפיק תלתא הוו. Hashta vadai ei l'hacha
nafik tlata havay v'ei l'hacha nafik tlata havay.
From A's perspective the one guy in B is with him, that
gets you three. From C's perspective the one guy in B is
with him, that gets you three. או דילמא אימא להכא נפיק ואימא
להכא
נפיק. o dilma eima l'hacha nafik v'eima l'hacha nafik. The guy in
B could in theory go either into A or into C and
since you don't know which one he's associated with, effectively neither A
nor C has three people. So the גמרא Gemara says והלכתא בעיין
לקולא. v'hilchasa ba'ayan lekula.
And the הלכה halacha is all of the questions we read, we
just asked, will be lenient. Sort of like a nice פשט pshat
of what we've been saying in עירובין, Eruvin, that we always go
leniently, alright? Except when we don't. Anyway, so that's the גמרא Gemara
having all that fun with the idea of this primary and secondary
space. Now you'll be pleased to know that we move on to
a different topic, although I thought, I thought that was quite fun.
Anyway, I guess that shows you how far we are in עירובין.
Eruvin. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רב חסדא,
amar Rav Chisda, גידור חמישה ומחיצה חמישה. giddur chamisha u'mechitza chamisha. Now
this is a discussion that is very relevant for הלכות שבת, Hilchos
Shabbos, you know, straight רשות reshus questions, not just עירובין Eruvin questions.
You've got a...
a גידור, giddur, like a platform,
like a raised space that's five.
גידור Giddur is not a gate or like
a גדר, geder, like a fence?
No, it's not. And you've got around it a wall that's five,
okay? And here you are, you're standing here. Now the question is,
are you in a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid or not? It looks
like a big chair. It looks like Tom's Thumb or something. Anyway,
okay,
here, we'll make it maybe this way so it makes sense to
you, it still looks like a chair. Anyway, do we say, maybe
it's because it looks like legs rather than... whatever. Anyway. So if
you were,
if you were on top of an entire thing that was ten,
you know, ten by four, you know, you'd be on a רשות
היחיד. reshus hayachid. Or obviously, if you had a wall and you
were on the ground, right, and the wall was ten, it'd be
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid because there's ten basically, you know, a
full ten, you know, here at least on the bottom and you're
a full height over ten and all these things have a full
ten. But here you have a height of only five and then
a wall of five. Okay, so if you're standing on the other
side, right, maybe it's a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid because you're looking
at a wall of ten. But on this side, you're not at
a height of ten and you don't have a wall of ten.
Are you on a רשות היחיד? reshus hayachid? That is the question.
So let's take a look. And we'll see what this is doing
in our גמרא Gemara in a minute.
אין מצטרפין, ein mitztarpin, they do not combine, עד שיהא כולו בגידור
או כולו במחיצה. ad sheyehei kulo b'giddur o kulo b'mechitza. Either all
of it is in the height,
or all of it is the wall. Okay, now we're going to
ask on this, but I just have to show you תוספות Tosafos
asks a great question. In the middle of תוספות Tosafos גידור חמישה
ומחיצה חמישה, giddur chamisha mechitza chamisha, תוספות Tosafos says וצריך עיון מעניין
שבת. v'tzarich iyun me'inyan Shabbos. If you look, it's like four lines...
last word on the line, sorry, last word on the line, just
this וצריך עיון מעניין שבת. v'tzarich iyun me'inyan Shabbos. אם יש תל
ברשות הרבים גבוה חמישה ורוחב ארבע ועל גביו עשו מחיצה חמישה. im
yesh tel bi'reshus harabbim gavoha chamisha v'rochav arba v'al gabav asu mechitza
chamisha. If you had this exact
scenario
in the middle of a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, שהזורק מרשות הרבים
לתוכו חייב מתוכו לרשות הרבים פטור. she'hazorek mi'reshus harabbim letocho chayav mitocho
l'reshus harabbim patur. תוספות Tosafos says, can you really have something that's
a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid only in one direction? Right? If that
were true, according to him, that it doesn't combine on this side,
but from the guy on the other side of it, the guy
standing here in the רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, right, he's looking at
a wall that's ten, right? So would you say, oh, if I
throw from here to here, I went from a non-רשות היחיד reshus
hayachid to a רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and I'm פטור. patur. But
if I throw from here to here, from my perspective, I was
looking at a רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and therefore I'm חייב. chayav.
So תוספות Tosafos says it's hard to imagine that that would be
true. He does not really tell you what the answer is.
But it's a nice little discussion about the two adjacent...
I know, it's similar to the fact that it has one reality
from one side and the other from the other. Okay, so let's
take a look though, this is the תוספות Tosafos point, that it's
not a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מתיבי, meisivei,
I'll ask you on this, says the גמרא. Gemara. שתי חצירות זו
למעלה מזו. shtei chatzeiros zo l'ma'ala mi'zo. You have two yards, one
higher than the other. העליונה גבוהה מן התחתונה עשרה טפחים. ha'elyona gvoha
min ha'tachtona asara t'fachim. And the top one is ten טפחים tefachim
higher, meaning they're like, you know, they're on a higher plateau. או
שיש בה גידור חמישה ומחיצה חמישה. o sheyesh bah giddur chamisha u'mechitza
chamisha. Or, according to this ברייתא, braisa, it's exactly that scenario, it's
five higher, you know, it's raised ground, five higher, and then there's
a five טפח tefach wall. מערבין שנים ואין מערבין אחד. me'arvin shnayim
v'ein me'arvin echad. They make two separate עירובין, eruvs, they can't make
one, meaning that's considered to be a full separation of the two,
that gets back to our earlier discussions, right, about what types of
walls fully separate the two courtyards, and they cannot make a unified
עירוב. eruv. פחות מכאן, pachos mikan, if the wall is lower, מערבין
אחד ואין מערבין שנים. me'arvin echad v'ein me'arvin shnayim. You can make
one and not two. So because you have to make one because
they're all one. So the question is, why is this true? So...
so you know, why is it... why is it that in this
case of these two courtyards, you have courtyard one and then you
have courtyard two which is a little bit... which is higher and
it's got this little wall? So it's got five here and it's
got wall five. Okay, you just said that this wall is not
a separation. So this... I mean, so if this wall is not
a מחיצה, mechitza, not a separation, they should be able to make
one big עירוב. eruv. Okay, so the answer is I a little
bit jumped ahead, so I sort of hinted to the answer. So
the answer is, it
says
אמר רב, Amar Rav, or what's that change to? אמר רבא: Amar
Rava: מודה רב חסדא בתחתונה העוברת על פני עשרה. modeh Rav Chisda
betachtonah haoveret al pnei asara. The bottom one, since it's looking at
a wall of ten, the bottom one is separated out. That was
the point I said, that from these guys' perspective it is a
wall. So since from their perspective it is a wall, they cannot
make an עירוב eruv together with these guys, because they are actually
looking at a whole wall of ten that is separating them. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ah, but what about these guys? So that's
what it's going to say. So it says like this: אי הכי,
Ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, תחתונה תערב שנים ולא תערב אחד.
tachtonah tearav shnayim velo tearav echad. The bottom courtyard has to make
a separate עירוב eruv because they are separated with a wall. עליונה,
Elyonah, and the top one, לא תערב לא אחד ולא שנים. lo
tearav lo echad velo shnayim. The top one is stuck. Okay, why?
Because from the top's perspective, okay,
can they make a separate one? They can't make a separate one.
Why can they not make a separate one? Because they're not divided
from this courtyard. So they're not entitled to make a separate one.
Can they make a unified one? They can't make a unified one.
To be unified, these guys have to have it has to be
one from this perspective as well. So these guys should be totally
stuck and not able to make an עירוב. eruv. They can't make
their own עירוב eruv because from their perspective they're not separate. They
can't make a unified עירוב eruv because from these guys' perspective they're
not they are separate. So they should be totally stuck. Okay, and
it still doesn't explain why it's saying that each one does it
separately. So the גמרא Gemara says like now you are seeing as
though before why it's relevant, because it has like working from one
direction and not from the other direction. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: לא תערב לא אחד ולא שנים. Lo tearav lo echad
velo shnayim. אמר רבה בר עולא, Amar Rabbah bar Ulla, כגון שהייתה
עליונה מגופפת עד עשר אמות. kegon shehayta elyonah megufefet ad eser amot.
So we're going to make a special case. Obviously it's a big
problem, but we're going to make a special case. If all of
the weak answers start to bother you, you should know the conclusion
is we're going to reject all this and say that this scenario
does count as a wall. But okay, but for now when we're
saying it's not, here's the answer. What's the answer? The answer is
is that this is not the only separation. That basically the rest
of it is this much bigger yard here, okay, and here you
actually have a wall that is, you know, whatever, although that's the
thing, the wall here extends in this part of it עשר אמות.
eser amot. And here it drops to five. Okay, and similarly like
this, it extends to ten. So therefore
because it extends to עשר אמות eser amot here, this then becomes
this scenario, right? Okay, that's sort of the three-dimensional view of that,
right? Okay, here it's ten, here it's five. Okay, and five doesn't
count as a wall. Okay, so therefore it says that in this
case they can make two they can make two what do you
call it? You know, two ערובין, eruvin, because since this allows A
to cut themselves off from B, therefore they're I mean, you know,
or you could sort of even imagine it like this, it doesn't
exactly have to be that case, right? It doesn't have to be
that it's smaller, just has to be that it's not totally open.
Okay, right, you see that's what anyway, so since A is allowed
to cut themselves off from B, they're allowed to make two ערובין.
eruvin. Okay, however, once it is lower than five, if it's lower
than five oh no, I'm sorry, I was right the first time.
If it's lower than five, so in this case they can make
two. But now what's B's story? B can also be separate. Why
can B be separate? Because from B's perspective this is five on
A's side but it's ten on B's side. Right, you see that?
So from B so from A's perspective we can make two because
we can cut them off. From B's perspective you can make two
because you got a מחיצה mechitza of ten. But what happens as
soon as that drops below the five wall? Then it becomes if
it becomes four and nine, A can still make their own עירוב,
eruv, but B is now stuck because it's פרוץ במלואו, parutz bimloo,
right, it's completely open. So therefore B in that case cannot make
their own עירוב. eruv. So what so the ברייתא Baraisa that says
that when this is five and five they're separate, okay, it's true.
That's what you need for them to be separate because as soon
as it gets less than five, it becomes therefore less than ten
for B, they can't be separate because B has to is completely
exposed to A. Alrighty, and so anyway, so a weak answer to
this ברייתא Baraisa which forces us to use a case that we've
been discussing. So it says like this: כגון שהייתה עליונה מגופפת עד
עשר אמות. Kegon shehayta elyonah megufefet ad eser amot. אי הכי Ei
hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, אימא סיפא: eima seifa: פחות מכאן, pachot
mikan, once the wall is less than five, you know, five, it's
built on five so it's five and five and it's less, מערבין
אחד ואין מערבין שנים. mearvin echad veein mearvin shnayim. One עירוב eruv
and not two ערובין. eruvin. So if that what really happens when
it gets less than five or
ten? אי בעי חד ליערב אי בעי תרי ליערב. Ei bei chad
layariv ei bei trei layariv. So really, so already I jumped ahead.
Okay, I'm sorry, I keep on jumping ahead. The first answer was
I'm sorry about that, the first answer was this case, okay, where
you had it like this. Okay, and therefore we said if this
is five here, it's ten here, and therefore if it's that height
you can do two. But then it goes on and says, but
one minute, it says if it drops below that, four and nine,
what does it say? It says מערבין אחד ואין מערבין שנים. marvin
echad ve-ein marvin shnayim.
But why in that case it says you have to be מערב
אחד? me'arev echad? If you've got something that's got a door, it's
got the partial wall on both sides, and so each side you
could still do separate. Why does it say when it gets less
than ten you have to make one? They could each be separate.
And then the Gemara says, oh, no, what we're talking about is
the case of פרוץ במלואו. parutz bemilo'o. And therefore when it gets
less than ten, you know, less than five here, less than ten
here, then B cannot separate itself off and therefore that's why you
can no longer be separate and you can only be together. So
the Gemara says like that.
It says כגון שנפרצה תחתונה במלואה לעליונה. kegon shenifretzah tachtona bemilo'ah la-elyona.
אי הכי iy hachi says the Gemara, if that's true,
תחתונה tachtona חד חטיה chad hatei תרי לא תבי trei lo tavi
is forced to make one eiruv because it's completely exposed to A,
its walls less than ten, so it's got to make one eiruv
with
A... תרי לא תבי. trei lo tavi. עליונה elyona the top one,
איבעי תרי תבי ibay trei tavi איבעי חד תבי. ibay chad tavi.
The top one though A isn't forced to make one eiruv, A
can still choose to separate itself off because it's still got a
wall on each side, right? A wall, you know, this partial wall
that enters in on each side. אין הכי נמי ein hachi nami
you're right. וכי תני פחות מכאן מערבין אחד ואין מערבין שנים vechi
tany pachos mikan marvin echad ve'ein marvin shnayim when it says when
the wall goes low you have to make one eiruv, אתחתונה atachtona
it's going on the lower one, on B. Okay, so basically what
we've said here is that we've had a real big problem because
this made it sound like the wall five was a real wall.
The only way we explained it was to create a special case
where it you anyway can be separate because there's a wall already
on each side, a partial wall already on each side, and that
allows you to be separate and that when it gets lower than
five, which means lower than ten on B side, A can still
choose to be separate but B becomes fully open and B has
to make one. A very complicated way of explaining that ברייתא baraita
which on the face of it clearly said that a five and
five scenario is a full wall. And the reason it's being discussed
here is because what it uses for the answer is the scenario
of the ad of the like, you know, B as the sub-courtyard
to A as B is fully exposed to A and A is
not fully exposed to B. And now we get thankfully the opposing
position which is actually how we rule.
So the Gemara says like this:
דרש מרימר. Darash Mareimar. So Mareimar though explicated: גידוד חמשה ומחיצה חמשה
מצטרפין. Gidud chamisha umechitzah chamisha mitztarfin. Thank God. That if you have
the mound five and the wall five it actually do combine and
it makes רשות היחיד reshus hayachid on both sides or מחיצה mechitzah
on both sides, okay, and therefore that simply then explains this whole
ברייתא baraita that is five and five and treats it as a
full מחיצה. mechitzah. אשכחיה רבינא לרב אחא בריה דרבא. Ashchei Ravina le-Rav
Acha brei de-Rava. So Ravina found Rav Acha
brei de-Rava, אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said to him: תני
מר מידי במחיצה? Tani Mar midi bimechitzah? Have you taught anything regarding
מחיצה? mechitzah? אמר ליה לא. amar lei lo. He said no.
Okay, so what's that doing here?
So some change the גרסא girsa so
to... if you look at the side here, where is it, the
ב, beis, it's... where is this other גרסא? girsa? I have another...
wait where is this גרסא? girsa? No, א. alef.
אמר אמימר מידי בגידוד חמשה ומחיצה חמשה? Amar Ameimar midi begidud chamisha
umechitzah chamisha? Have you heard Ameimar's position regarding this issue of five
and five? And he said no. So anyway clearly somehow the question
was in context of this five and five and he either denied
either knowing what Ameimar's position was or denied having a position of
his own about this. והלכתא, Vehilchesa, the הלכה halacha is, גידוד חמשה
ומחיצה חמשה מצטרפין. Gidud chamisha umechitzah chamisha mitztarfin. Okay, so that's the
simple read of that ברייתא baraita although it did create again it
was a... it's funny to you know you see how they have
fun, you know, with these types of things like a מחיצה mechitzah
from one direction and not from the other direction, but the simple
sense of the ברייתא baraita and therefore the הלכה halacha is is
that the five and five actually make a מחיצה mechitzah on both
sides and not just on one side. Okay, בעי רב הושעיא. Ba'ei
Rav Hoshaya. Now Rav Hoshaya asks: דיורין הבאין בשבת. Diyorin habaim b'Shabbos.
Now this actually is not directly related to this whole major and
minor courtyard case, okay, and it's a separate question which in one
way or another we've had before. דיורין הבאין בשבת מהו? Diyorin habaim
b'Shabbos mahu? Let's say guests drop in on Shabbos, dwellers. Now it
doesn't literally mean it. What it means is the configuration changes on
Shabbos. So some people that were not considered part of the courtyard
on Shabbos became part of the courtyard, like a wall fell
down, okay. מהו שיאסרו? mahu sheye'asru? Do they make it forbidden? So
we'll see a scenario in a minute. אמר רב חסדא תא שמע,
Amar Rav Chisda: Ta shema, come and hear. חצר גדולה שנפרצה לקטנה.
Chatzer gedolah shenifretzah leketanah. So again this is our case which is
why it's being brought here. הגדולה מותרת והקטנה אסורה מפני שהיא כפתחה
של גדולה. Hagedolah muteres ve-haketanah asurah mipnei she-hi kipischa shel gedolah. Because
it is it's like the opening. Now it says he is focusing
on the word of שנפרצה, shenifretzah, that it burst forth, and he
assumes what that means is that
What would we do without a whiteboard? Okay, he assumes what that
means is that when שבת Shabbos began it looked like this. When
שבת Shabbos began it looked like this. And then it says שנפרצה
shenifretzah that the wall that the wall opened up. And therefore what
happens? A remains מותר, mutar, B is אסור assur because it's totally
exposed. But he's reading the scenario, the wall fell down on שבת.
Shabbos. So B, which was מותר mutar when שבת Shabbos began because
the wall was there, when the wall falls down, B becomes אסור.
assur. So he says, you see, when it changes on שבת, Shabbos,
that does create problems, even if when שבת Shabbos began it was
okay.
What's happened before, we've seen that whatever things, however things were on
שבת. Shabbos.
Yes, so we're getting there. Okay, but again, like I said, this
discussion has come up before. Okay. So, people being born. Yeah, yeah,
yeah. Okay, anyway, so he says, מפני שהיא כפתחה של גדולה. mipnei
shehi kefitchah shel gedolah. אמר רבא, Amar Raba, so
רבא Raba said, אימא מבעוד יום נפרצה. eimar mibod yom nifretzah. You
don't have to read that that meant that it burst open on
שבת. Shabbos. Let's say the wall fell down from before שבת. Shabbos.
אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye,
so אביי Abaye said, לא תימא מר אימא. lo teimar mar eimar.
You should, you know, the master, you, רבא, Raba, should not say,
well, it's possible you could say that it means that the wall
fell down before שבת. Shabbos. אלא ודאי מבעוד יום נפרצה. Ela vaday
mibod yom nifretzah.
It definitely means that it fell down before שבת Shabbos and, and
once שבת Shabbos starts, it remains the way it was when שבת
Shabbos starts. It does not change on שבת Shabbos itself. Now, why
is אביי Abaye being so insistent? דאמר, De'amar, because he's talking to
רבא, Raba, and he says, you, רבא, Raba, you, הוא דאמר, hu
de'amar, you, this is your position, that things are, that things remain
from the way they were when שבת Shabbos began. How do you
know this? דאמר הוא דבעי מיניה מרב הונא. De'amar hu de'ba'ei minei
me'Rav Huna. You asked רב הונא. Rav Huna. ובעי מיניה מרב יהודה.
U'ba'ei minei me'Rav Yehudah. And you asked from
רב... Rav... sorry, דאמר הוא דאמר, de'amar hu de'amar, you said to
me, בעי מיניה מרב הונא, ba'ei minei me'Rav Huna, ask רב הונא,
Rav Huna, ובעי מיניה מרב יהודה, u'ba'ei minei me'Rav Yehudah, and ask
from רב יהודה, Rav Yehudah, עירוב דרך הפתח ונסתם הפתח. eruv derech
hapetach venistam hapetach. You made an עירוב eruv through an opening because
of the opening and then it got filled up on שבת. Shabbos.
Or עירוב דרך החלון ונסתם החלון, eruv derech hachalon venistam hachalon, window
that got filled up, מהו? mahu? What's the story? Which means, it's
basically the case of you have two courtyards, you have your A
and your B, and there's an opening here. And because of the
opening, you made an A B עירוב, eruv, okay, because of the
opening. And then comes שבת Shabbos and this opening gets filled, okay.
So what is the הלכה? halachah? Does it, can you, does it
ruin the עירוב? eruv? Are you still allowed to, like, you know,
put things over the wall and whatever, and still allowed to go
from A to B? Or does the fact that it got filled
ruin the עירוב? eruv? You told me to ask that question. ואמרו
ליה, Ve'amru lei, and you said to me, or they said to
me, it was, it's funny, it's plural and singular, it's not exactly
clear. שבת כיון שהותרה הותרה. Shabbos keivan shehutar hutar. Since שבת Shabbos
started off permissible, that was good when שבת Shabbos began, it remains
good. So you basically say that if it remained okay when שבת
Shabbos began, it doesn't change. And similarly, if the wall was here
when שבת Shabbos began and fell down afterwards, B's status would not
change. B remains the way it was when שבת Shabbos began. Okay,
and that's where we'll end for for today.